This is the story of the first ever use
of a weapon of mass destruction.
>> Very recently, the weapon we are about
to deliver was successfully tested in
the States. We have received orders to
drop it on the enemy. It is the most
destructive weapon ever produced.
>> The target was an empire with its own
[music] secret weapon, the suicide
bomber.
>> I trained myself that I could die at any
time.
>> We've got Nyaga, Kakura, Nagasaki, and
Hiroshima.
Hiroshima was an important military
base, the headquarters of the second
general army with a key role in the
[music] defense against the expected
invasion.
>> Advice bomb primary. It's Hiroshima.
Long way.
It took about 45 seconds from the time
the bomb left the airplane until it
exploded. And I think there wasn't a man
in the airplane that wasn't either
timing it with his watch or counting or
doing something. I was sure the bomb was
a dud. I was sure it wasn't going to
work.
After falling for 43 seconds, the time
and barometric triggers started the
firing mechanism. A uranium bullet fired
down a barrel into a uranium target.
Together, they started a nuclear chain
reaction.
Solid matter began to come apart,
releasing untold quantities of energy.
Heat.
There was a white light in the window, a
flash, white like magnesium.
The bomb delivered its destruction in
stages.
The flash came from a giant fireball 300
m wide.
I was astonished.
It was a startling light. Even if you
had your back turned to it, you felt the
shock go through right to the center of
your brain. At the same time, any area
of skin that was exposed became very
hot.
>> Heat. Such burning heat.
>> Temperatures directly below the fireball
were 4,000° C. The heat rays left
shadows. Ladders, railings, even people
left their outlines on stone and metal.
Anyone
in the open air was either vaporized or
turned to carbon in an instant.
At the same time, the flash sent out
powerful infrared radiation and gamma
rays.
These could penetrate walls and attack
the cells in human bodies.
Then I slowly opened my eyes and for the
first time looked in the direction of
the light.
>> Just at that moment, a mushroom cloud
appeared.
People who saw this in Hiroshima are
nearly all dead by now.
There is barely anyone left now who can
say they actually saw it happen. behind
us more.
>> A fraction of a second later came a
powerful shock wave which moved at the
speed of sound. It turned everyday
windows and walls into shrapnel.
As soon as the blast hit, I was thrown
across the room.
My body was flung from wall to wall and
from the ceiling to the floor.
>> My body was thrown around like it was a
ball.
>> A jet black belt of cloud came towards
me. It came from there over the lip of
the mountain.
The black cloud spread between the
mountains and came rolling in my
direction, swirling like this.
Just like that, my body was scooped up.
It was the blast. It sent me flying
through the house.
>> The flash was very brilliant and it only
lasted a very short period of time. It
was over in a
few short seconds.
We didn't see any bodies down there or
anything of that type. Uh you didn't see
any buildings collapse. You can't really
distinguish things like that. And even
if we had been able to, we couldn't do
it anyhow because there was just a it
was all covered with smoke and dust and
everything.
I'm not emotional. I didn't have a first
goddamn thought or ought to tell you
what it was.
I did the job and I was so relieved that
it was successful. You can't understand
it.
Seeing the fires on the ground and the
cloud coming up, then you get
pretty uh distressed that there's such
havoc down there and people are
suffering.
There are no exact figures for the
number who died in the instant of the
explosion, but tens of thousands of
people in the open near the fireball
vanished in a fraction of a second.
For the survivors, the ordeal was just
beginning.
Thousands of people were injured and
terribly burned. Many were trapped in
the rubble.
>> Just 260 m from the bomb, the two girls
in the bank had been sheltered from the
worst of the explosion by the earthquake
proof building.
When the girls struggled outside, they
found a vision of hell.
The morning sunshine was gone. The whole
city was dark and shrouded with smoke.
The streets were full of corpses.
The words city of death came to mind.
There were only dead people. We were the
only living souls.
>> It had been the morning commuting hour,
8:15 in the morning. People that had
been walking the streets were doubled up
dead over each other for as far as we
could see.
They had died immediately, naked, burnt.
I just asked myself why and could not
find any words.
[panting]
The two of us just crouched down and
burst into tears.
How could such terrible things happen
at the communications hospital one mile
from the explosion's hypo center. Nurse
Kinuko was blown away from the window.
Like so many others, she was badly
lacerated by flying glass.
I have pieces of glass sticking up from
my body all over from my head, my face,
my body.
The drill ground was less than a mile
from the hyper center.
20-year-old Cadet Morioaki had gone
inside the barracks building just before
the bomb exploded. His colleagues
outside were exposed to the full heat
flash.
They were all either dead or gravely
burned.
Hi Rashima Castle, which had been there
in front of my eyes, had gone.
Everybody was covered in blood. The
wooden buildings had been smashed to
pieces.
In another part of the city, she gay
Heratsuka's peaceful family breakfast
had given way to chaos and confusion.
>> When we got out, we saw that the whole
of Hiroshima had been turned upside
down. None of the buildings were left.
Fires were breaking out in different
places all over the city.
Then I looked around for the children.
[screaming]
>> There was my daughter Kaspo. She was
six.
>> She was buried from the chest down and
wedged in by timber and plaster.
>> I tried to get her out. I was desperate
to [crying]
But whatever I tried wouldn't work.
>> The fires were moving closer and closer.
The flames were at our feet and roaring
up around us.
We could not stand the heat and pain any
longer.
[crying]
No.
[screaming]
Okay. [crying]
He got
the school building had also collapsed.
In the blast,
8-year-old Takashita Namorei and his
friends were trapped in the rubble,
crying out for someone to rescue them.
>> First things I saw was a pitch darkness.
>> Then I could sense the several soldiers
above my head moving the debris
and the final one soldier dug me out.
All I remembered that as the soldier
clutch me in his arms, weaving through
the fires between the fires.
The only place we are able to escape is
the river which runs behind our school.
[music]
Near the station about 2 mi from the
flash, Teruko Fuji thought her tram had
shortcircuited on the overhead cables
and that the whole thing was her fault.
>> I thought I'd caused some kind of
disaster. I thought I'd broken the tram
and done something terrible. didn't it?
>> And then I thought, is it a bomb? That
was when I realized that it wasn't me
who' caused all this trouble.
>> First, I thought only the station area
was affected, but then I saw people
walking towards me with injuries and
skin hanging from them.
Everybody thought perhaps if I go over
there I could be saved.
>> People to the west thought the east
might be better.
>> People were going in every direction in
total silence.
Amid all the destruction, there was at
least one miracle.
8-year-old Takashi Tanamorei [music] was
carried through the burning city by the
soldier who rescued him. At last, the
soldier reached a river and from the
crowds, the little boy heard a familiar
voice.
>> Somehow my father spot me.
I guess he called in my name and I maybe
I responded and I said that's my daddy.
And then he stood straight toward the
soldiers and he bowed many many times to
the soldiers said, "Thank you. You are
savior."
Later on after we were flying back,
conversations started about, you know,
the war being over as a result of this
bomb. Despite the number of people we
killed, we saved multiple numbers over
that for being in a war and being killed
on American side, on the Japanese side.
That time there was such a hatred for
the Japanese that the more we killed,
the better off we thought we were
because that means there was going to be
less that we're going to have to contend
with during the invasion.
>> After a 6-hour return flight, the Anola
Gay reached Tinian Island.
There probably three, four, 500 people
there. And when we get out of the
airplane, why? Of course, we're all
getting out. We're tired and everything
of that type. And I get out. I remember
getting out carrying my oxygen mask. I'm
right behind Paul.
And um then some joker calls us to
attention. I got out of the airplane
like I was told. He p this thing on my
shirt. Guys are taking pictures of it. I
salute him. And after that was over
with, back to my duty. We're got to go
to debriefing by the intelligence
people. They had certain things, Dak,
did you see this? Did you see that? And
so forth confirming that we had bombed
the right target.
Guy said, "Sure.
Dr. Aida escaped from the rubble of the
farmhouse 4 miles outside Hiroshima.
After checking on the child he had been
treating, he headed back towards the
city.
>> It's about 6 kilometers to Hiroshima.
From there,
when I was halfway there, suddenly a
strange creature appeared out of
nowhere.
As it was summer, if it were human, it
would have been wearing white. What I
saw was all black from top to bottom.
Pitch black. I thought it was strange.
At the top, there [music] was something
round like a head. It had shoulders.
Something like a body followed.
>> But it was like it had no face. It was
black. The area around the eyes had
swollen up. It had nose. The lower half
of the face was just mouth. It was
frightening.
As a doctor, the first thing you do is
take a pulse. But when I took his hand,
there was no skin. There was nowhere I
could hold.
So I stood up saying please pull
yourself together and walked around him.
>> This person gave a small shudder and
then he stopped moving.
He had died.
He had fled three kilometers and then
died there.
That man was the first fatality caused
by the bomb that I saw.
Army recruit Shigaru Terasawa had been
stationed seven miles from the center of
the blast.
His unit was sent to help survivors, but
they soon faced a terrible conflict
between their compassion and their
training.
>> Even now, there are things that I will
never forget.
One is the sound of people begging me
for water.
In those days, we had been told not to
give water to the badly burned.
To tell you the truth, we all had these
big military water flasks on our hips.
People
were begging for water, but we didn't
give them any. We had been told that if
we did, they would die straight away.
And so, I didn't give them any. A lot of
people died.
Now, looking back, I wish I had given
them water.
Burned and bleeding in the intense heat,
people were desperate to find any water
they could.
They fled to the rivers, to pools and
reservoirs. Among them, nursed Kinuko.
>> I knew there was a pool of water in the
backyard of the hospital.
Lots of people had already got into the
pool. More people had jumped on top of
them.
The people underneath drowned.
This is one scene I can never forget.
I still dream about it.
Then came a strange deliverance.
Dark raindrops [music] began to fall
from the clouds above the burning city.
>> [music]
>> We opened our mouths and drank it.
Our throats were parched, but it was
difficult to capture the rain into our
mouths.
[music]
The rain was made black by ash and smoke
which had been sucked up into the rising
mushroom [music] cloud.
When these ashes mixed with cool, humid
air in the upper atmosphere, they formed
thick black raindrops [music] and fell
back down onto the city.
[music]
>> The drops of rain were big enough to
hurt when they hit your skin.
>> It descended in a torrent. Black fluid
flowed where the rain fell.
>> It was raining black fluid.
What the people who drank the rain
didn't realize was that it was highly
radioactive.
In time, it would poison many [music]
thousands.
On the day the bomb was dropped,
President Truman was still traveling
home from Europe.
On our way back on the Augusta,
returning to Washington, we were on the
edge of our chairs because we expected
any day, any time, any day to have a
flash from the War Department that uh
the first bomb had been dropped. And on
August 6th, as we were about one day out
from Norolk, we that flash came,
>> George Elsie decoded the telegram that
brought the news to President Truman on
the Augusta.
When something like that came, we would
walk it to immediately. We would
interrupt whatever he was doing. He
happened to be having lunch with the
crew at that point.
took it to Truman who showed it to
Secretary Burns and to Admiral Ley. And
then Truman announced to the ship's crew
this great accomplishment.
>> We have dropped a single bomb on the
Japanese city of Hiroshima
with the power of 20,000 tons of TNT.
The city has been COMPLETELY DESTROYED.
>> [cheering and applause]
>> was cheering. Cheering by the crew,
cheering by the officers when he read it
in the officer's mask.
[cheering and applause]
>> The Augusta was one of the ships that
was destined for the uh Pacific and
would have been involved in the
invasion. And uh uh the crew knew that
just about everybody who was in Europe
knew that they were headed would be
headed for the Pacific and an invasion
of Japan. So they were just as overjoyed
as as the president was that this damn
thing is over.
>> We hope this will be a warning to the
Japanese military.
Come on, boys. WE'RE GOING HOME.
>> HE WAS EAGER to get home because he was
sure that the word the Japanese
surrender would would come very soon.
>> In case there was any doubt, Truman
spelt it out to the Japanese high
command.
It was to spare the Japanese people from
utter destruction that the ultimatum of
July the 26th was issued at Potan.
Their leaders promptly rejected that
ultimatum.
If they do not now accept our terms,
they may expect a reign of ruin from the
air the like of which has never [music]
been seen on this earth.
Late that afternoon, the mayor of
Hiroshima issued [music] his own
proclamation.
The present catastrophe is the result of
a horrible and inhuman air raid.
The enemy's intention is clearly to
undermine the fighting spirit of the
Japanese people.
Citizens of Hiroshima,
the damage is great, but that is only to
be expected during a war.
Keep up your spirits.
Do not lose heart.
the morning after the bomb. A fullscale
rescue [music] effort began.
Squads of soldiers from surrounding
garrisons [music] were drafted in to
help.
They collected [music] the dead bodies
and disposed of them before disease
could spread.
The wounded were quickly taken away for
treatment.
Makeshift hospitals were set up,
although there were only a handful of
medical staff.
Dr.
found himself treating 3,000 survivors
in a village outside Hiroshima.
>> At first, we had no medicine, no
equipment.
There was nothing we doctors could do.
However, we gathered up some things and
started treating the burns.
>> Nurse Kinuko had an extraordinary
escape.
>> [music]
>> I don't know whether I was unconscious
for hours or for days.
When I did come round, I thought, "So, I
am still alive. God must have given me
strength."
>> She woke to [music] find that she had
been thrown into a mass grave.
After I crawled out of the hole, I
managed to cross the road to get to the
entrance of the hospital.
[music] It took me a terribly long time
as I could not stand nor lift my arms or
move them to the side.
I crawled like an insect and finally
reached the hospital entrance.
Dr. Hinoi from the pharmacy spotted me
and exclaimed, "You're still alive."
>> He picked me up and carried me to the
surgery area.
The corridor was full of people lying
side by side.
This was where they operated on me
>> and removed all of the large pieces of
glass that were stuck in me.
>> All over the city, relatives search the
ruins for signs of survivors. Before
midday, my friend's father came to get
us.
But my friend, who had escaped from the
bank with me, [music] turned out to have
a broken spine.
She died a week later.
How did you say?
>> She was a year younger than me.
>> I am nearly 80 years old now, but she
was only 18 at the time.
>> Whenever I think of her, she is still 18
years old.
She was a very pretty, gentle person.
Nurse Kinuko decided to make her own way
home. She crawled from the hospital as
far as Hiroshima station,
but no trains were running.
[music]
I was told that I had to go to the next
station to get on a train.
I asked myself what the best way to get
there would be.
[music]
I didn't know the roads.
I realized the only way was to crawl
along the railway track and that was how
I got to the next station.
>> Several times I lost consciousness.
>> Sometimes I woke up to see blue sky.
other times to black sky.
[music]
>> In the end, I reached the station.
Kinuko [music] finally reached her
hometown where she was nursed for many
months by her mother who had given her
up for dead.
3 days after the Hiroshima bomb, despite
all the destruction, Japan still hadn't
surrendered. A second bomb was made
ready, and Truman issued another
warning.
>> The world will note that the first
atomic bomb was dropped on Hiroshima, a
military base. If Japan does not
surrender, bombs will have to be dropped
on more industries.
I urge Japanese civilians to leave
industrial cities immediately and save
themselves from destruction.
I realize the tragic significance of the
atomic bomb. Having found the atomic
bomb, we have used it. We have used it
against those who attack us without
warning at [music] Pearl Harbor.
Against those who have starved and
beaten and executed American [music]
prisoners of war. Against those who have
abandoned all pretense of obeying
international laws of warfare.
We have used it in order to shorten the
agony of war, in order to save the lives
of thousands and thousands of young
Americans.
The second bomb was intended for the
city of Kokura, but it was too cloudy,
so the plane moved on to Nagasaki.
Desperately short of fuel, the crew
released the bomb despite more clouds.
The bomb missed the aiming point and
fell into a valley.
This time, there was no firestorm, but
even so, more than 50,000 people were
killed.
The Supreme War direction Council in
Tokyo was meeting on the same day. By
now, the Russians had declared war on
Japan. Then came the news from Nagasaki.
What you can do?
forchech.
Fore
speech.
Then Prime Minister Suzuki did something
unheard of. He asked the emperor to
break the deadlock and make a decision.
Emperor Hirohito told them he wanted to
end the suffering and bear the
unbearable.
4 days later, radical soldiers attempted
a coup to prevent the surrender.
They failed.
At dawn, on the day that Emperor
Hirohito was to broadcast an
announcement to the Japanese people that
the war was over, General Anami prepared
to end his life in the timehonored
tradition [music] of Sepuku.
His
suicide note read, "My death is my
apology for my great crime.
[music]
The war was over.
At last the troops were going home.
There was jubilation around the world.
But then came something that would
forever change perception of the bomb.
It started in the hospitals.
A mysterious illness began to spread. I
noticed it from about the fourth day.
>> Of course, it had been there all along,
but I thought people were dying of
severe burns.
The woman who lost her children in the
fires, she gay Heratica and her husband
were amongst those affected.
>> They lined my bed up next to my husband
and took his test first.
>> When they had taken enough blood for the
sample, they withdrew the needle.
>> What do they do?
>> But the blood wouldn't stop.
Nothing worked. Whatever they did.
Even when they applied pressure, it
carried on bleeding.
>> During this time, purple spots began
breaking out all over my husband's body.
He then vomited a large amount of brown
liquid.
Afterwards, he went limp and died an
hour later.
He had managed to survive that far. But
then even he was taken away from me.
Her
husband was one of thousands [music] who
would die from this new and untreatable
condition.
>> They were rotting. It was necrosis.
>> There were no white blood cells, so the
blood had no power to fight against
infection. And so suddenly the rotting
set in the end. The hair would start to
fall out. When you put your hand on the
patient's head, tufts of hair would come
away in your hand.
>> It emerged that those who were worst
affected had been close to the
hyperenter or had swallowed radioactive
material like the people who drank the
black rain.
In hindsight, we realized that it was
radiation. But at that time, we didn't
know what it was.
Radiation sickness has become the single
most disturbing legacy of the bomb.
American scientists had always known the
bomb would produce radiation, but the
scale of the after effects came as a
shocking surprise.
Today, Hiroshima is a thriving city of
over a million people.
Japan too [music] has been transformed
into a prosperous country that has
renounced the use of war entirely.
Although no one has used a nuclear
weapon since, arguments [music] continue
as to the morality of dropping the bomb.
Was it really necessary?
Could it have been avoided?
>> The nation had no rice to eat. People
had not eaten white rice for a whole
year. How could such a country go to
battle? The Americans knew that very
well and still dropped the atomic bomb.
Why? It was an experiment. They knew
that the bomb had enormous explosive
power. What they did not know was how
much damage the radiation would cause.
Some scientists thought they knew, but
they had not tested it. So they made an
experiment to find out by testing it on
human beings. The final decision that
resulted in the two bombs, Hiroshima and
Nagasaki, was not made in Potam. It
wasn't made by Truman. It was made by
the Japanese militarists when they
rejected any opportunity to surrender
just their armed forces and save further
massive loss of life.
Today, there are just a few places that
bear the scars of August the 6th, 1945.
There are burn marks on trees.
The shadow of a vaporized man left
[music] on stone.
Firstand memories are fading too.
Ako Takura, the bank clerk, who had been
just 260 m from the hyper center, is one
of the last witnesses to the full horror
of the bomb.
>> There is a department store called So in
Hiroshima, where I stop sometimes for
tea.
From the T-room, I can see the road from
the bank to the drill ground where we
escaped.
I see old people walking happily down
the street. Young people holding hands
and enjoying each other's conversation.
Children holding their parents' hands
and looking happy.
And I think about those awful scenes
that I experienced many years ago now
and all the people that lost their
lives.
I think to myself, what was all that?
Did it really happen?
Every year on the 6th of August, there
are ceremonies to recall what took place
on that day,
to make sure that these events are never
forgotten or repeated.
At sunset, tens of thousands of candles
are released on the river in Hiroshima.
Each candle representing the soul of one
of the dead.
[music]